PROFESSOR: Today we want
to discuss wave packets.
We have studied already
the motivations that
led to the Schrodinger
equation and we even
included the potential
that described
very non-trivial dynamics.
With that Schrodinger equation,
you could jump and solve
the hydrogen atom, you could go
and do the harmonic oscillator
and all kinds of things.
But we might as
well develop, still,
our tools and intuition
of what's going on.
And quite a lot of intuition
comes from the free particle.
And the free particle
is interesting
because you can go beyond the de
Broglie wavelengths and the de
Broglie waves.
You had a single plane wave
representing a particle
with momentum and with
energy, but now you
become more sophisticated and
consider the superposition
of those waves.
So we'll begin by discussing the
wave packets and uncertainty.
So it's our first look into
this Heisenberg uncertainty
relationships.
And to begin with, let's
focus it as fixed time, t
equals zero.
So we'll work with
packets at t equals zero.
And I will write a
particular wave function
that you may have at
t equals 0, and it's
a superposition of plane waves.
So it would be e to the ikx.
You sum over many of them, so
you're going to sum over k,
but you're going to do it
with a weight, and that's 5k.
And there's a lot
to learn about this,
but the physics that is encoded
here is that any wave at time
equals 0, this psi of
x at time equals 0,
can be written as a
superposition of states
with momentum h bar k.
You remember e to the ikx
represents a particle or a wave
that carries momentum h bar k.
So this whole idea here
of a general wave function
being written in this way
carries physical meaning
for us.
It's a quantum
mechanical meaning,
the fact that this kind
of wave has momentum.
But this phi of k,
however, suppose
you know this wave
function at time equals 0.
Phi of k is then calculable.
Phi of k can be
determined, and that's
the foundation of what's called
Fourier's theorem, that gives
you a formula for phi of k.
And it's a very similar formula.
1 over 2 pi, this time
an integral over x.
So you take this of
psi of x0 that you know
and then multiply by
e to the minus ikx.
Integrate over x, and out
comes this function of k.
So if you know phi of
x0, you know phi of k.
You can calculate this interval
and you can rewrite phi of x0
as a superposition
of plane waves.
So that's how you would do
a Fourier representation.
So somebody can give you
an initial wave function,
and maybe it's a sine function
or a Gaussian or something,
then what you would do if
you wanted to rewrite it
in this way, is calculate phi
of k, because you know this psi,
you can calculate this integral,
at least with a computer.
And once you know
phi of k, you have
a way of writing psi as a
superposition of plane waves.
So we've talked
about this before,
because we were doing
wave packets before
and we got some intuition about
how you form a wave packet
and how it moves.
Now we didn't put the
time dependence here,
but that can wait.
What I wish to
explain now is how
by looking at these
expressions, you
can understand the uncertainties
that you find on the wave
function, position, and
momentum uncertainties,
how they are related.
So that is our real
goal, understanding
the role of uncertainties here.
If phi of k has
some uncertainty,
how is the uncertainty
in psi determined?
So that's what
we're looking for.
So relationship
of uncertainties.
Now as before, we
will take a phi of k,
that we've usually be in
writing, that depends on k
and it's centered
around some value k0.
It's some sort of nice,
centered function.
And it has then, we
say, some uncertainty
in the value of the momentum.
That is this signal,
this phi of k
that we're using to
produce this packet.
It has some uncertainty,
it's not totally sharp,
it's peaked around k0
but not fully sharp.
So the uncertainty
is called delta k
and it's some typical
width over here.
Delta k is then uncertainty.
Now it's not the purpose
of today's lecture
to make a precise definition
of what the uncertainty is.
This will come later.
At this moment, you
just want to get
the picture and the
intuition of what's going on.
And there is some
uncertainty here,
perhaps you would say,
look at those points
where the wave goes from
peak value to half value
and see what is the width.
That's a typical uncertainty.
So all what we're going
to do in these arguments
is get for you the intuition.
Therefore, the factors
of 2 are not trustable.
If you're trying to make
a precise statement,
you must do precise definitions.
And that will come
later, probably
in about one or two lectures.
So at this moment, that's
the uncertainty, delta k.
And let's assume that
this phi of k is real.
And its peaked around
k0 uncertainty delta k.
Now what happens with psi of x?
Well, we had our statements
about the stationary phase
that you already are practicing
with them for this homework.
If you want to know where
this function peaks,
you must look where
the phase, this phi--
we say it's real, so it doesn't
contribute to the phase--
where the phase, which
is here, is stationary,
given the condition that
it should happen at k0.
The only contribution
to the integral
is basically around k0.
So in order to
get something, you
must have a stationary
phase, and the phase
must be stationary
as a function of k,
because you're
integrating over k.
And the phase is
kx, the derivative
with respect to k of
the face is just x,
and that must vanish, therefore,
so you expect this to be
peaked around x equals zero.
So the x situation, so psi
of x0 peaks at x equals 0.
And so you have a picture here.
And if I have a picture, I would
say, well it peaks around the x
equals 0.
So OK, it's like that.
And here we're going to
have some uncertainty.
Here is psi of x and
0, and here is x.
And let me mention, I've already
become fairly imprecise here.
If you were doing
this, you probably
would run into trouble.
I've sort of glossed over
a small complication here.
The complication
is that this, when
I talk about the peaking
of psi, and you probably
have seen it already, you have
to worry whether psi is real
or psi is complex.
So what is this psi here?
Should it be real?
Well actually, it's not real.
You've done, perhaps,
in the homework already
these integrals, and you
see that psi is not real.
So when we say it
peaks at x equals 0,
how am I supposed to plot psi?
Am I plotting the real
part, the imaginary part,
the absolute value?
So it's reasonable to
plot the absolute value
and to say that psi absolute
value peaks at x equals 0.
And there will be some width
again here, delta x, width.
And that's the
uncertainty in psi of x.
So the whole point of our
discussion for the next 10
minutes is to just
try to determine
the relation between
delta k and delta x
and understand it intuitively.